Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.0

(April 5th, 2006)

Contents

Introduction
List of Updates (Change Log)

Introduction

As of version 6, TrueZIP has developed from a Java based virtual file system for ZIP32 files to a Java based virtual file system for basically any archive type! This has been achieved by the introduction of a plug-in driver architecture. As of this release, the following archive families are supported out of the box:

ZIP32 archives including relatives such as JAR and RAES encrypted ZIP32 files.
TAR archives including relatives such as TAR.GZ and TAR.BZ2.

Future versions will see support for additional archive types, such as ZIP64 (currently planned for TrueZIP 6.1).

Happy zipping! (and tarring and tar.gzipping and tar.bzip2ing...)

Legend
New | Introduces a new feature.
Fixed | Introduces a bug fix of an existing feature.
Enhanced | Introduces the enhancement of an existing feature. This update is fully backwards compatible.
Changed | Introduces the change of an existing feature. This update may cause backwards incompatibilities .
Deprecated | Introduces the deprecation of an existing feature.

List of Updates (Change Log)

The generalization from supporting only ZIP32 archives to virtually any archive type has made some refactorings of the public API inevitable. This opportunity has been used to introduce some more refactorings of the low level APIs, too. This affects primarily the classes for the RAES implementation (the RAES specification has not changed) and the Swing based password manager (which has now become a general key manager with a pluggable user interface). All these changes have been made in order to make the code base much more extensible, which is expected to reduce the need for future refactorings of the public API.

This means you must recompile your client applications if they have been using TrueZIP 5 before. If this is unacceptible to you, you may opt to stay with TrueZIP 5. TrueZIP 5 will be continued to be maintained for a while. However, it is recommended to migrate to TrueZIP 6 in order to benefit at least of its enhanced performance.

The changes in the high level API in the package de.schlichtherle.io have been kept to a minimum and are quite obvious, so it should be easy to migrate your client application. For a head start, please see below.

About the TAR Plug-In Driver Family

Although the TAR archive file format is widely used, it is also pretty much obsolete (its in use since the early 70ies). The main issue with it from TrueZIP's point of view is that it does not support a central directory. So the first time you do this:

String[] members = new File("my-killer-app-sources.tar.gz").list();

... the entire archive is going to be decompressed on the fly and its entries are extracted to your temp file system for future use! Of course, this is not acceptable if your client application is going to do a quick listing on a big TAR file only. But it's still the most efficient strategy if your application is going to work on the archive subsequently - traversing its directory tree, copying, renaming or deleting its entries, etc.

The good news is that TrueZIP's plug-in driver architecture is flexible enough so that another driver could be implemented which behaves differently (you can even install the driver at runtime, just when you discover that you need it). Hence, a smarter driver could be implemented which decompresses the archive entries based on heuristics. For example, the driver could load the file system in memory and then again decompress the entire archive when one of the archive's entries is requested for the first time. However, in case of a compressed TAR archive (using GZIP or BZIP2 for example) the downside of this strategy is that the archive would need to be decompressed twice: The first time to construct the virtual file system from its entries and the second time to extract one or more of these entries. As you can see, neither solution is optimal.

In case you're worried about the persistence of the temporary files, please note that they stay resident until either of the following happens:

Explicitly: The client application calls File.update() or File.umount() to tell TrueZIP that its finished with the archive.
Implicitly: The client application does not hold any reference to the archive or any of it entries anymore and the finalizer picks up TrueZIP's internal cache data.
Implicitly: The client application terminates - TrueZIP uses a JVM shutdown hook for cleanup.

Because of this issue with the TAR file format, an application's performance could easily be downgraded if a TAR file is hit by accident. In order to avoid this, the ".tar", ".tar.gz", ".tgz", ".tar.bz2" and ".tbz2" file suffixes are not recognized by default! In order to make your application recognize these suffixes, you must use an ArchiveDetector object (the successor to the ZipDetector used in versions up to TrueZIP 5.1.X). For example, to recognize these suffixes with all your File* classes instances, you could do:

File.setDefaultArchiveDetector(DefaultArchiveDetector.ALL);

In fact, this is what the nzip utility main class does. As an alternative, you could also pass an ArchiveDetector explicitly to the constructor of the File* classes or change the default suffixes in the plug-in driver configuration resource file (see the Javadoc on the DefaultArchiveDetector class for more information).

About the TAR.BZ2 Driver

Due to various issues with the BZIP2 implementation in Ant 1.6.5, the driver for TAR.BZ2 archives is considered to be experimental - use with care only!

In particular, the driver is slooowww and very exhaustive on memory. It's memory usage is even so exhaustive that the JUnit tests for the ".tar.bz2" suffix run about half an hour and then failed with an OutOfMemory error (in contrast to about 76 seconds for the same tests with ".tar.gz"!). So you should use this driver only with small archives.

Credits

I am very thankful to the Apache Software Foundation for the TAR code in Ant 1.6.5! Thanks to this I did not have to write the low-level part of the TAR driver myself.

How to get going with TrueZIP 6

To see TrueZIP 6 in action, you will need the following:

The latest JAR for TrueZIP "truezip.jar". You can download it here.
For TAR support: "ant.jar" from Apache Ant Version 1.6.5 or higher. You can download Ant at http://ant.apache.org.
For RAES encrypted ZIP file support: Bouncy Castle's Lightweight Crypto API for JDK 1.4 Version 1.30 or higher. Check for "lcrypto-jdk14-130" at http://www.bouncycastle.org/latest_releases.html.
For Javadoc: You can read the Javadoc online here.
For source code: The source distribution of TrueZIP "truezip-src.zip". You can download it here.
For unit testing: JUnit 3.8.1 or later. You can download JUnit at http://junit.org.

To play around with it, I recommend to start running the nzip utility main class first. For a tutorial on this utility, read this section.

To start using the API, I recommend to read the Tutorial for TrueZIP Version 6 and then read the source code of the nzip utility main class to see the changes in the API which were inevitable in order to move TrueZIP from a ZIP-only virtual file system to a generic-archive virtual file system.

Implementing plug-in Archive Drivers

Implementing a plug-in driver for custom archive types is comparably easy. The package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi contains the interfaces which you need to implement. It has been kept as simple as reasonable. Please refer to the Javadoc of this package for more information.

Once implemented, you need to register your driver with the class DefaultArchiveDetector. Please refer to its Javadoc for more information.

If you have implemented a pure Java based archive driver for a reasonable well-known archive type and don't mind sharing it with the community, I would be happy to add it as a contribution! Please send an email to christian at schlichtherle.de in this case.

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.1

(July 10th, 2006)

Contents

Introduction
List of Updates (Change Log)

Introduction

This is a bug fix and minor feature release. The primary focus has been to fix multithreading issues and enhance the Javadoc. The new feature is the extension of the ZIP archive driver family with CRC-32 checked versions for optional usage. Updating is considered critical for multithreaded environments such as application servers.

New CRC-32 checked ZIP archive drivers

TrueZIP now supports checking of the CRC-32 value in existing ZIP archive files. While this feature has been available for a while in the class de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipFile (as opposed to java.util.zip.ZipFile), it wasn't used by the ZIP archive driver family in the package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip. With TrueZIP 6.1. a number of new drivers have been introduced to support this feature:

Default Driver | Optional driver
Does not check the CRC-32 value in existing archives | Does check the CRC-32 value in existing archives
JarDriver | CheckedJarDriver
ReadOnlySfxDriver | CheckedReadOnlySfxDriver
Zip32Driver | CheckedZip32Driver

Because CRC-32 checking comes at a notable performance penalty, the checked archive drivers are just optional and hence are not used by default. If you think that this is an issue, please bear in mind that any application based on the class java.util.zip.ZipFile currently does not support CRC-32.

 If you want to use these optional drivers for increased safety, you either (1) have to create a custom instance of the class de.schlichtherle.io.DefaultArchiveDetector or (2) provide a custom version of the configuration file META-INF/service/de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi.ArchiveDetector.properties on your classpath. For the first approach, please refer to the Javadoc and have a look at the source code for the nzip utility in the default package. For the second approach, please have a look at the default configuration file within truezip-6.jar.

If you are using the checked ZIP archive drivers, the CRC-32 value of any input stream referring to an archive entry is calculated and compared to the CRC-32 value provided in the archive file as soon as you call the close() method of the input stream. If there is a mismatch, the close() method throws a de.schlichtherle.util.zip.CRC32Exception.

More unit tests

Some more JUnit tests have been added to the test directory in order to test multithreading and the GUI of the Swing based implementation of the Key Manager in the package de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing. All tests have been run on the following combinations of JDKs and platforms and should be running on all other platforms with the same JDK as well:

Sun's JDK 1.4.2-b28 for Windows^1
Sun's JDK 1.4.2_12-b03 for Windows
Sun's JDK 1.5.0-b64 for Windows^12
Sun's JDK 1.5.0_07-b03 for Windows^2
Sun's JDK 1.6.0-beta2-b86 for Windows

The tests de.schlichtherle.io.FileTestBase.testMultithreading1() and de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipTestBase.testMultithreading() may or may not fail with an OutOfMemoryException. This does not constitute an issue with TrueZIP. If this happens, simply try to increase the maximum memory available to the JVM using the -Xmx switch (-Xmx100m for example). Later versions of the JDK do not show this issue, so I guess this is because of a change in the garbage collection algorithm.
The test de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.PromptingKeyManagerTest.testMultithreadedKeyMgmtLifeCycle() will most likely fail on this combination of JDK/platform. Again, this does not constitute an issue with TrueZIP. This is because the Jemmy library calls Thread.sleep(10), which actually sleeps much longer for an arbitrary amount of time and hence causes Jemmy to timeout.

For the GUI tests to run you now need to have Jemmy 2.2.6 or later in your class path. You can download Jemmy at http://jemmy.netbeans.org. Please note that the test de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.PromptingKeyManagerTest.testMultihreadedKeyMgmtLifeCycle() runs in Robot mode and hence will hijack your mouse and keyboard for the duration of the test (aprox. 2 minutes). Do not change the window during this test, or you will get a bad surprise from all the input that would then be received by the other window!

Legend
New | Introduces a new feature.
Fixed | Introduces a bug fix of an existing feature.
Enhanced | Introduces the enhancement of an existing feature. This update is fully backwards compatible.
Changed | Introduces the change of an existing feature. This update may cause backwards incompatibilities .
Deprecated | Introduces the deprecation of an existing feature.

List of Updates (Change Log)

Following is an overview of all updates in this release which affect the public API. Please note that internal refactorings are not listed. For a full list of updates, please refer to the CVS repository and diff to the tag TrueZIP-6_0.

Multithreading

Fixed: The classes de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipOutputStream and de.schlichtherle.io.OutputArchiveMetaData dead locked each other if used in multithreading environments. This affected the public File* classes in the package de.schlichtherle.io.
Fixed: de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi.AbstractArchiveDriver.ensureEncodable() threw a RuntimeException if used in multithreading environments. This affected most classes in the package de.schlichtherle.io.
Fixed: de.schlichtherle.io.ArchiveEntryMetaData.list*() threw an AssertionError if used in multithreading environments and assertions were enabled. If assertions were disabled, wrong results may have been produced. This affected the methods de.schlichtherle.io.File.list*().
Fixed: de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipFile.getInputStream() threw a ZipException if used in multithreading environments. This affected the class de.schlichtherle.io.FileInputStream.

Key Manager

The Key Manager in the package de.schlichtherle.key has undergone some changes/enhancements:

Fixed: KeyManager.setInstance() was always ignored.
Fixed: KeyManager.resetAndClearKeyProviders() always threw a ConcurrentModificationException.
Enhanced: The method KeyManager.getKeyProvider(String, Class) can now determine a more suitable class substitute for the second parameter, e.g. if the second parameter is AesKeyProvider.class. This provides better support for loose coupling between client applications and key provider implementations.
Changed: The Swing based implementation of the Key Manager, which is located in the package de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing, has been more or less rewritten in order to fix some bugs (including multithreading issues) and provide a more maintainable and extensible code base. The impact of this change should be minor because these classes were a specific implementation of the Key Manager service and were not for public use anyway unless a client application needed to customize this implementation.

Miscellaneous

Fixed: de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipFile.getCheckedInputStream() returned a buggy input stream: The CRC32 was only correctly computed (and hence the check in the close() method run successfully) if the input stream was read until the end of file using either read(byte[]) or read(byte[], int, int) and neither read() nor skip() were used.
Enhanced: On a CRC32 mismatch in a ZIP file, the close() method of the input stream returned by de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipFile.getCheckedInputStream() now throws a de.schlichtherle.util.zip.CRC32Exception, which is a new subclass of de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipException, which was thrown instead before. In case the configured ZIP driver supports this feature (see next section), the close() method of the class de.schlichtherle.io.FileInputStream throws this exception, too.
Fixed: Depending on the use case, the private event listener code in de.schlichtherle.swing.EnhancedPanel threw a NullPointerException from the AWT event dispatch thread.
Fixed: Removed obsolete get/setDosTime() methods from de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip.Zip32Entry class.
Enhanced: PanelEvents fired by de.schlichtherle.swing.EnhancedPanel are now coalesced, so that for each event cause only one event is generated, no matter how the Swing API is utilized by the client application to show or hide an ancestor window.
Enhanced: The logging in de.schlichtherle.io.DefaultArchiveDetector has been refined in order to provide more suitable messages for tracking down class loader issues.
Enhanced: The Javadoc for many classes has been reviewed and fixed or enhanced.

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.2

(August 7th, 2006)

Contents

Introduction
List of Updates (Change Log)

Introduction

This is a maintenance and feature release. The primary focus has been to optimize multithreading performance, fix minor bugs and enhance the Javadoc. Updating is recommended for multithreaded environments such as application servers.

Feedback for Swing based key prompting

Until this release, TrueZIP blocked the current thread and AWT's Event Dispatching Thread for three seconds if a user entered a wrong key in the default Swing based Key Manager implementation. This was intended to prevent robots trying passwords systematically.

As of now, a new Feedback interface hierarchy has been introduced instead. The run() method of this interface is called whenever a password dialog is showing. Implementations are expected to start visible/audible feedback to the user without blocking the current thread, which is AWT's Event Dispatching Thread. So if the implementation wants to show an animation, it should use the class javax.swing.Timer.

The default implementation for the InvalidOpenKeyFeedback interface (named BasicInvalidOpenKeyFeedback) just sounds a beep and disables the OK button in the enclosing JOptionPane for three seconds, effectively inhibiting the use of robots for automatic password trying again. If application developers want to provide a sexier implementation, they should subclass BasicInvalidOpenKeyFeedback, provide a public no-arguments constructor and put the class name in the system property de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.InvalidOpenKeyFeedback.

An example is already provided with TrueZIP, but not enabled by default: The class de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.QuakingWindowFeedback will show a nice earthquake effect on the password dialog box for a second. The idea for this class has been taken from the great book "Swing Hacks" by Joshua Marinacci & Chris Adamson, though this implementation provides a bit more realistic effect. If you would like to see it in action, use the nzip utility main class like this:

java -cp "truezip-6.jar;lcrypto-jdk14-130.jar" nzip mkdir test.tzp
java -cp "truezip-6.jar;lcrypto-jdk14-130.jar" nzip ll test.tzp

Note: On non-Windows platforms, substitute the ";" with a ":".

This will create an RAES encrypted ZIP file named "test.tzp" in your current directory and then list its contents (which are empty, hence no output). To see the earthquake effect, simply provide a wrong password on the second command.

Browsing files with a JComboBox

Auto completion of file names is a much liked feature of any decent command line shell (such as the bash). But why leave all the fun only for command line shells? The class de.schlichtherle.io.swing.FileComboBoxBrowser is here for your rescue: It provides users with a comfortable means to use auto completion for file names in a regular JComboBox.

To use this class, do something like this:

JComboBox box = new JComboBox();
new FileComboBoxBrowser(box);
box.setEditable(true);

The second line is where the magic happens: It creates a new FileComboBoxBrowser and attaches it to the previously created JComboBox. Now if a user starts entering any character into the combo box, it will be interpreted as the beginning of an absolute or relative path name. All possible completions are then put into the popup window and shown. Then the user can use the arrow keys on his keyboard to pick his favourite file or directory. This repeats until the focus leaves the editing text component of the combo box.

As usual with TrueZIP, this component allows to browse archive files (e.g. ZIP files), too.

Experiments have shown that this is a very powerfull feature: Using this combo box is usually much faster than the JFileChooser. Of course, in a professional client application you should offer both a JComboBoxBrowser and TrueZIP's custom implementation of the JFileChooser in the class de.schlichtherle.io.swing.JFileChooser, so that the user can pick files or directories (even within an archive file) using either way.

Legend
New | Introduces a new feature.
Fixed | Introduces a bug fix of an existing feature.
Enhanced | Introduces the enhancement of an existing feature. This update is fully backwards compatible.
Changed | Introduces the change of an existing feature. This update may cause backwards incompatibilities .
Deprecated | Introduces the deprecation of an existing feature.

List of Updates (Change Log)

Following is an overview of all updates in this release which affect the public API. Please note that internal refactorings are not listed. For a full list of updates, please refer to the CVS repository and diff to the tag TrueZIP-6_1.

New/Enhanced: The interaction between the RAES key authentication code and the KeyManager has been refined so that the GUI is not blocked for three seconds anymore if the user has provided a wrong key. Instead, a new Feedback interface hierarchy has been introduced to provide advanced feature options. Read more...
New: The class de.schlichtherle.io.swing.FileComboBoxBrowser has been introduced in order to provide users with a comfortable means to use auto completion for file names in a combo box. Read more...
Enhanced: The virtual file system now uses a custom read/write lock mechanism to enhance concurrency: Multiple threads may read an archive concurrently while at most one thread may write/modify it at a time.
Fixed: The constructor de.schlichtherle.io.DefaultArchiveDetector(String) did not throw an IllegalArgumentException when an unknown suffix was passed, as opposed to the Javadoc.
Enhanced: The class de.schlichtherle.io.DefaultArchiveDetector now logs at the WARNING level if the DEFAULT entry in a configuration file names an unknown archive suffix.
Enhanced: The methods get/setParentWindow in the class de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.PromptingKeyManager have been changed in order to prevent memory leaks and return the active window as the default. In consequence, client applications do not normally need to call setParentWindow(Window) at all anymore.
Changed: The class de.schlichtherle.swing.event.PanelAdapter has been made abstract in order to reflect its use case.

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.3

(October 6th, 2006)

Contents

Introduction
List of Updates (Change Log)

Introduction

This is a minor feature release which adds some new parameters to make it easier to update/unmount archive files safely in multithreaded environments.

Legend
New | Introduces a new feature.
Fixed | Introduces a bug fix of an existing feature.
Enhanced | Introduces the enhancement of an existing feature. This update is fully backwards compatible.
Changed | Introduces the change of an existing feature. This update may cause backwards incompatibilities .
Deprecated | Introduces the deprecation of an existing feature.

List of Updates (Change Log)

Following is an overview of all updates in this release which affect the public API. Please note that internal refactorings are not listed. For a full list of updates, please refer to the CVS repository and diff to the tag TrueZIP-6_2_1.

New: The methods de.schlichtherle.io.File.update/umount(...) provide new parameters which make it easier to update archives safely in multithreaded environments: You can now update individual archive files only and/or wait until all other threads have closed their archive entry streams. Furthermore, you can now specify the forced closing of entry streams separately for input and output streams. For more information, please refer to the Javadoc.
Fixed: Ghost directories (directories for which there is no information present in an archive, but for which one or more children exist) were written to the archive on update.
Fixed: A ClassCastException was thrown when updating an archive on some non-Sun provided J2SE APIs.
Fixed: The prologue length for an empty ZIP file was set to Long.MAX_VALUE. This caused the empty ZIP file to be prepended to any update of the ZIP file, which didn't negatively affect ZIP file format compatibility but unnecessarily bloated the updated ZIP file by 22 bytes on each update.
Fixed & Enhanced: Updated the Javadoc of some classes.

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.4

(December 21st, 2006)

Contents

Introduction
List of Updates (Change Log)

Introduction

Though this is a minor version number release, it's a major improvement. The primary focus has been to fortify the code and optimize it: Many bugs were fixed, accompanied by new or enhanced JUnit tests in order to prevent future regressions. Furthermore, performance has been significantly improved in some sectors, especially if a client application happens to deal a lot with false positive archive files, TAR files or RAES encrypted ZIP files. In addition, the Swing based key prompting GUI has now been extensively tested on Linux in order to fix some bugs which only showed on this platform.

Upgrading is highly recommended for everybody!

Legend
New | Introduces a new feature.
Fixed | Introduces a bug fix of an existing feature.
Enhanced | Introduces the enhancement of an existing feature. This update is fully backwards compatible.
Changed | Introduces the change of an existing feature. This update may cause backwards incompatibilities .
Deprecated | Introduces the deprecation of an existing feature.

List of Updates (Change Log)

Following is an overview of all updates in this release which affect the public API. Please note that internal refactorings are not listed. For a full list of updates, please refer to the CVS repository and diff to the tag TrueZIP-6_3_2.

Cross Package Updates

Enhanced: In addition to the default Swing based key manager class de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.PromptingKeyManager, the classes de.schlichtherle.crypto.io.raes.Type0RaesReadOnlyFile and de.schlichtherle.key.SharedKeyProvider now both enforce a three second suspension penalty if a wrong key was provided. This has been added for protection against exhaustive key searches by malicious key provider implementations or abuses of even friendly implementations. The delay has no recognizable effect on the Swing based key manager because the key provider UI implementations used by this key manager already enforce the same suspension penalty by disabling the OK button for three seconds.
Enhanced: InputArchive and OutputArchive in the package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi implementations do not need to be thread safe at all anymore. The synchronization is now completely handled by the archive controller and its companion meta data classes. This fixes some synchronization issues with the TAR driver and potentially the ZIP driver.
Enhanced: Javadoc here and there.

Updates in the Base Package

New: The nzip utility main class has two new commands: "isArchive" prints whether a file system node is a prospective archive file and "length" prints the length of a file system node. These commands may be useful in scripts.
Enhanced: The utility main classes now include version information when printing their usage (finally).

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.awt

Enhanced: Added the method invokeAndWaitInterruptibly to the class EventQueue in order to interrupt AWT's Event Dispatch Thread (EDT) too, if the waiting thread was interrupted. The method invokeAndWaitUninterruptibly now logs with the FINE level in case an interrupt was attempted.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.crypto.generators

Enhanced: Seeding algorithm in constructor of class DigestRandom to make creation of instances an order of a magnitude faster - at least on Linux, where the SUN provider's SHA1PRNG implementation uses the slow, but secure /dev/random device. This significantly improves performance when working with lots of RAES encrypted ZIP files on Linux, as the salt for each file is created from a new, self-seeding DigestRandom object.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io

Fixed: The JVM shutdown hook in the class ArchiveController did not delete the temp files unless the client application called File.umount() after the last modification. This was a regression and used to work in earlier versions.
Fixed: Wrong initialization if "dot-only" paths ("", ".", "./", "./.", ...) were passed as the child parameter to the "parent constructor" File(java.io.File parent, String child, ArchiveDetector detector).
Fixed: The synchronization strategy in the package private classes (In|Out)putArchiveMetaData has been revised in order to to completely exempt archive drivers from the need to be thread safe. This fixes some racing conditions and dead locks which were known to be present with the TAR driver family and potentially the ZIP driver family, too.
Fixed: The method File.delete() sometimes returned true where it should have returned false, in particular when called on archive files which still have open input streams.
Fixed: The method File.cp(File, File) accepted source and destination files which effectively referred to the same file or where the source contained the destination. This resulted in undefined behaviour. Now a ContainsFileException is thrown instead.
Fixed: The method File.cp(File, File) sometimes failed to copy false positives, i.e. a node in the file system which appears to be an archive file, but actually is something else (a regular directory or plain file). In particular, this was true when copying entries within the same false positive directory, i.e. entries in the same regular directory. For the same reason, as opposed to its contract, File.cp() did throw an InputIOException instead of a FileNotFoundException if the input file or any of its parent directories was a false positive.
Fixed/Enhanced: The class DefaultArchiveDetector had some bugs when instantiated with obscure constructor parameters like uppercase file suffixes or null arguments. It has been reimplemented to work with collections and thread locals for enhanced performance and maintainability.
Fixed: When an input stream for an entry in an otherwise unmodified archive file was used which's File instance hasn't been kept, the stream was sometimes arbitrarily closed. This happened because the archive controller was mistakenly garbage collected. The package private classes InputArchiveMetaData and OutputArchiveMetaData have been fixed to hold a strong reference to the archive controller now, so that the archive controller is strongly reachable from any entry stream.
Enhanced: The methods File.listFiles(*) now always return an array of File instances instead of just an array of java.io.File instances entirely populated with File instances. This is in preparation for the migration to Java 5 where these methods will also explicitly declare this return value in order to get rid of those ugly type casts.
New: The classes File(Reader|Writer) have been added as drop-in replacements for the equal named classes in the java.io package.
Enhanced: The ArchiveController class now protects the access to its file system with a state pattern in order to remember false positive archive files. In case of the unit tests for the File class, this results in three times faster performance, primarily because the unit tests are testing false positive archives a lot! The state is reset when File.delete() is called on the false positive archive file or File.update() or File.umount().
Enhanced: If running on JSE 5 or later, TrueZIP automatically takes advantage of the cached thread pools available in the java.util.concurrent package when copying data asynchronously. This provides some performance benefits. Full backwards compatibility to J2SE 1.4.2 is retained.
Enhanced: File.setLenient() now also controls how TrueZIP shall behave on unclosed archive entry streams: If set to false, a hard reference to all archive entry streams is maintained by TrueZIP, causing an ArchiveBusy(Warning)?Exception to be thrown on the next call to File.update() or File.umount() in case of an unclosed archive entry stream. If set to true (the default), then TrueZIP behaves as before and will close archive entry streams when they are garbage collected, reducing the likeliness of an ArchiveBusy(Warning)?Exception to be thrown on the next call to File.update() or File.umount(). This is to support testing client applications for the presence of the "unclosed streams issue".
Enhanced: ArchiveController.mkdir(*) doesn't try to mount the file system anymore if the target file exists already. This avoids to prompt for a key in case the target file is an RAES encrypted ZIP file although the key is not really required at this time and slightly enhances the performance.
Deprecated: File.getDelegate(). This method exists for technical reasons only! In case you want to convert an instance of this class which recognized the leaf of its path as an archive file to a file instance which doesn't recognize this archive file, use the following code instead: ArchiveDetector.NULL.createFile((File) file.getParentFile(), file.getName()).
Fixed: File.createNewFile() failed for entries in a false positive archive file which is actually a native directory.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi

New: The class TransientIOException may now be used by archive drivers to signal that an IOException occured as a transient event when accessing an archive file and another try to access the same archive file may finally succeed. On the other hand, if the archive controller catches an IOException from an an archive driver when trying to access an archive file which is not a TransientIOException, then the archive controller may consider the archive file to be a false positive and cache the exception until File.umount() or File.update() is called. This is used by the RAES encrypted ZIP file driver family when prompting for passwords has been cancelled by the user and another attempt to prompt the user should be allowed.
Enhanced: The archive driver specification has been relaxed so that InputArchive and OutputArchive implementations do not need to be thread safe anymore. The synchronization is now completely handled by the archive controller and its companion meta data classes. This fixes some synchronization issues with the TAR driver and potentially the ZIP driver, too. Old drivers will work to the specification, obviously.
Enhanced: TransientIOException has been added to the Javadoc of the methods ArchiveDriver.createInputArchive and ArchiveDriver.createOutputArchive. Since this is an IOException, existing archive drivers are not affected.
Changed: The classes InputArchiveBusyException and OutputArchiveBusyException are now subclasses of FileBusyException in order to simplify the cause chain: Previously, a FileBusyException may have had an (In|Out)putArchiveBusyException as its cause.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.tar

Fixed: The storeDirectory method in the TarOutputArchive class did not set the entry size to zero before writing the directory entry although it has never written any data to it. This caused interoperability issues with some tools when TAR files have been created on Unix: Most notably, Ant's TarInputStream class failed on the resulting archive files (GNU TAR accepted it).
Enhanced: TarInputArchive now uses a smarter read ahead algorithm to validate TAR files. However, only raw TAR archives benefit from it due to a bug in Sun's J2SE 1.4.2_12 (has been fixed in JSE 1.5.0-b64) which requires a workaround to render it useless. Check the source code for details.
Enhanced: Due to the relaxed archive driver specification, TarOutputArchive doesn't need to be thread safe anymore and so the redundant synchronization has been removed for better performance.
Enhanced: The TarBZip2Driver now uses buffered I/O for the underlying stream for much better performance. It also provides a new constructor argument to set the block size for the BZip2 algorithm - the default is the maximum block size. The new test case for this driver uses this to set the block size to the minimum in order to reduce the exhaustive memory occupation of the BZip2 implementation in the Ant code and make the test work. Warning: This driver is still experimental: Ant's underlying BZip2 implementation is very exhaustive on memory and slow (I'm not sure whether this is an implementation issue or a general issue with the BZip2 specification). Do not use this driver in productive environments for other than small archives! If you need to use it nevertheless, use Ant 1.7.0 RC1 or later. The BZip2 implementation in this version has been much improved and is required to pass TrueZIP's comprehensive unit tests for the File class with this driver.
Enhanced: The TarDriver class now offers a new method for overriding: createInputStream(ReadOnlyFile). When writing a custom driver, you should override this method instead of createInputArchive(Archive, InputStream) in order to support proper closing of all streams in the chain. TarGZipDriver and TarBZip2Driver have been revised appropriately.
Enhanced: Javadoc in almost all classes.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip

Fixed: The class Zip32OutputArchive produced corrupted file entries if and only if any of the methods copy(All)?(To|From) or cp in the class File in the package de.schlichtherle.io were used and a ZIP file entry in the source used the STORE rather than the DEFLATE method. Note that the methods archiveCopy(All)?(To|From) or cp_p were not affected. Likewise, no data was corrupted if the source didn't contain ZIP file entries or none of these entries used the STORE method.
Enhanced/Fixed: The Checked* driver classes have been changed to use the new feature of the ZipFile class in the package de.schlichtherle.util.zip to read deflated data while concurrently checking the CRC-32 value of the inflated data. The primary effect is to fix a bug which could have potentially corrupted data when copying entry data between archives operated by two ZIP drivers which handle checking differently. Another nice side effect is that these classes now support Direct Data Copying (DDC), which obsoletes the need to recompress data when copying an entry between two archives. This further implies that updating RAES encrypted ZIP files is now faster.
Enhanced: Due to the relaxed archive driver specification, Zip32(In|Out)putArchive don't need to be thread safe anymore and so the redundant synchronization has been removed for better performance. The superclass of these classes are now the newly introduced BasicZip(File|OutputStream) classes in the package de.schlichtherle.util.zip.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip.raes

Enhanced: The class AbstractZip32RaesDriver now provides an optional constructor parameter to adjust the authentication trigger, which is the largest size of an archive file which's RAES provided Message Authentication Code (MAC) will be checked. This defaults to Long.MAX_VALUE and may be overridden by subclasses (such as SafeZip32RaesDriver) in order to provide a different means to verify the integrity of an encrypted archive file.
New: ParanoidZip32RaesDriver has been introduced: This archive driver always authenticates input archive files using the RAES provided Message Authentication Code (MAC) before the archive can be accessed by client applications. This can take quite a while for large archive files. This driver is now advertised accordingly in the configuration file.
Enhanced: The authentication strategy in SafeZip32RaesDriver has been refined: For input archive files up to 512 KB, the cipher text gets authenticated using the RAES provided Message Authentication Code (MAC) before the archive can be accessed by a client application. For larger input archive files, the MAC is not used, but instead the CRC-32 value of the decrypted and deflated archive entries is checked when the archive entry stream is closed by the client application, resulting in some IOException. For more information why this operation mode is considered safe, please refer to the Javadoc.
Changed: UnsafeZip32RaesDriver has been deprecated and is no longer advertised in the configuration file.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.rof

Enhanced: The class ReadOnlyFileInputStream now supports marking if the underlying ReadOnlyFile does.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.swing

Fixed/Enhanced: FileComboBoxBrowser now sorts nicely using a Collator for the default locale; case is now always ignored when auto completing; plain java.io.File instances can now be used for the directory, too; a few initialization bugs have been fixed.
Fixed: JFileChooser may have dead locked when used to browse RAES encrypted ZIP files. This has been fixed at the cost of proper repainting when prompting for keys.
Enhanced: JFileChooser now shows correct icons and type descriptions for false positive archive files.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.util

Fixed: The utility methods in the class Paths did not always deliver correct results. This negatively affected the way some other classes, most notably the class de.schlichtherle.io.File interpreted paths. In addition, the methods have been moved from Path to Paths again and Path has been deprecated. Backwards compatibility on source code level has been retained, however.
New: Synchronized(In|Out)putStream as synchronized stream decorators. Used as utilities in some other classes.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.key

Enhanced: The contract in PromptingKeyProviderUI has been extended so that an implementation may optionally throw a RuntimeException with an UnknownKeyException as its cause in order to abort the prompting without the PromptingKeyProvider instance to change its state. This is useful when the prompting thread has been interrupted, in which case a subsequent attempt should still proceed instead of being automatically cancelled without actually prompting.
Fixed: Potential synchronization / dead lock problems in the key manager and key provider classes.
Enhanced: The abstract class KeyManager now loads its default implementation by class name in order to remove the compile time dependency on the sub package. In case you are using a class optimizer, don't forget to add all subclasses of KeyManager to the list of classes which are never renamed or discarded.
New: If the JVM is running in headless mode and the API conforms to JSE 6 (the class java.io.Console is available), then the console I/O based key manager implementation in the class de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.console.PromptingKeyManager is used instead of the Swing based key manager implementation in the class de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.PromptingKeyManager.
Changed: The classes Prompting(Aes)?KeyProvider now simply return their base class names as the UI class identifiers instead of their full class name. Client applications should not be affected, however.
Changed: The class SharedKeyProvider has been renamed to AbstractKeyProvider because of its misleading name. A deprecated stub class with the old name is retained as a sub class of the new name in order to maintain backwards compatibility.

New Package de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.console

New: This package has been added to provide a simple key manager implementation which uses console I/O to prompt the user for passwords. This key manager is used by default if the JVM is running in headless mode and the API complies to JSE6 (i.e. the class java.io.Console is available)!  To request it explicitly, set the system property de.schlichtherle.key.KeyManager to de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.console.PromptingKeyManager. This key manager does not support key files and disables prompting if no console is attached to the JVM.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing

Fixed: The classes in this package were likely to cause dead locks if the JFileChooser class in the package de.schlichtherle.io.swing was used to browse RAES encrypted ZIP files. This was caused by the implementation of the base class in the javax.swing package and its associated Basic L&F File Loader Threads.
Fixed: The method getParentWindow in the class PromptingKeyManager did not always return the correct window.
Fixed: The event listening in CreateKeyPanel and OpenKeyPanel has been refined so that the Feedback implementation instance is not run every time you switch between password entry mode and key file entry mode. In addition, on Linux, the focus is now properly moved to the input fields upon invalid input. This involved a change in the class AuthenticationPanel, too.
Enhanced: For reliability reasons, CreateKeyPanel now ensures that a key file is read-only.
New: The class HurlingWindowFeedback has been introduced as the successor to QuakingWindowFeedback - the latter is now a sub class of the first. HurlingWindowFeedback has also been improved to use Math.sin(*) to modulate the amplitude of the hurling. Have fun!
Enhanced: The class hierarchy for the Feedback interface and its standard implementations starting with BasicFeedback has been revised to make the standard implementations more reusable. The effect is that the HurlingWindowFeedback implementation can now also be used as the feedback when mismatching passwords or illegal key files for a newly created or updated RAES encrypted ZIP file is entered. In fact, this is the default configuration when using the nzip main class utility. As a result of this, some classes and interfaces have been marked as deprecated.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.swing

Fixed: AbstractComboBoxBrowser now properly initializes the combo box before the first input.
Enhanced: The class EnhancedPanel fires its PanelEvents synchronously again instead of posting them to the Event Queue, thereby reducing event listening problems of some classes in the package de.schlichtherle.key.passwd.swing.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.util.zip

Fixed: Potential racing conditions in ZipFile.getPreambleInputStream() and ZipFile.getPostambleInputStream().
Enhanced: The Zip(File|OutputStream) classes have been refactored so that they now subclass the newly introduced BasicZip(File|OutputStream) classes. Since the relaxed archive driver specification does not require the ZIP driver to be thread safe anymore, the ZIP driver family uses these new subclasses for better performance.
Enhanced: The new method getInputStream(String, boolean, boolean) in the class ZipFile now optionally supports reading of deflated data while checking the CRC-32 value of the inflated data in the close() method of the returned entry input stream. This is used by the checked ZIP driver family in the package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip and others in order to support the Direct Data Copying (DDC) feature.

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.5.4

(February 27th, 2007)

Contents

Introduction
List of Updates (Change Log)

Introduction

This is a feature and update release. Upgrading is recommended for all users.

Support for OpenDocument Format (ODF)

Most notably, support for reading and writing OpenDocument Format (ODF) files has been added. Here's an example:

// Recognize ODF text documents as created by OpenOffice Writer, e.g.
File.setDefaultArchiveDetector(new DefaultArchiveDetector("odt"));

File document = new File("helloworld.odt");
File content = new File(document, "content.xml");
try {
    FileInputStream in = new FileInputStream(document);
    try {
        // Init DOM parser here...
    } finally {
        in.close(); // ALWAYS close the stream!
    }
} catch (IOException ex) {
    ex.printStackTrace(); // maybe document is a false positive
}

If you want to create or modify an ODF file, make sure to create or overwrite the entry manifest first in order to provide best performance. Otherwise, the ODF archive driver buffers all output in temporary files until either this entry is written or the archive file gets unmounted. This is because ODF files must always start with this entry.

It is hoped that TrueZIP 7 alias TrueVFS can enhance the support for ODF files so that encrypted ODF files can be read and written transparently, too (just like RAES encrypted ZIP files are today). For this to work, TrueVFS would need to take full control over the entry META-INF/manifest.xml and probably hide its existance from the client application.

Creation and Ordering of Archive Entries

Directory archive entries are now only created in the output archive file if they have been explicitly created with File.mkdir() or their last modification time has been modified with File.setLastModified(long). Otherwise, they will just exist as so-called ghost directories in the virtual file system. Just like before, ghost directories can also be read from the input archive file and return 0L upon a call to File.lastModified(). This mimics the behavior of most archive tools, which do not write directory entries at all. The concept of ghost directories is now documented in detail in the Javadoc for the package de.schlichtherle.io.

When reading and writing archive files, the order of their entries is now preserved due to a change from HashMap to LinkedHashMap in some classes. Note that directory entries are still written after all file entries, if at all (see above).

These changes imply that when copying archive files, the order of the entries in the destination now more closely resembles the order in the source and that missing directory entries in the source (called ghost directories) are no longer created in the destination.

Concurrency

The ZIP driver family now supports concurrent writing of archive entries, just like the TAR driver family did already. Previously, an OutputArchiveBusyException was thrown. Don't expect wonders however: An archive file can still only get written as an output stream. So only the archive entry output stream which was first created will directly write to the archive file output stream. All others will write to a temporary file which will be copied to the archive file output stream when the archive entry output stream is closed and no other streams are busy or when the archive file gets unmounted (which closes all archive entry streams first).

Of course, thread safety has been unaffected by these changes: TrueZIP's virtual file system operations were and are virtually atomic. While not new, this concept is now documented in detail in the Javadoc for the package de.schlichtherle.io.

Miscellaneous

Great efforts have been put into the Javadoc. There is also a new tutorial/manual on the web site which covers the frequently asked questions. I hope you appreciate.

As usual, some minor optimizations and bugs have been fixed and the unit tests have been extended to cover regressions for the fixes in future releases. TrueZIP 6.5 has been analyzed with FindBugs in order to eliminate potential bugs. All remaining issues have been checked to be false positives.

Starting from this release, the precompiled JAR contains full debugging information. This should make a developer's life a bit easier: While it's easy to use tools like ProGuard to strip the debugging information if you don't want it, you don't need to do the more complicated build from the sources anymore if you need it.

Legend
New | Introduces a new feature.
Fixed | Introduces a bug fix of an existing feature.
Enhanced | Introduces the enhancement of an existing feature. This update is fully backwards compatible.
Changed | Introduces the change of an existing feature. This update may cause backwards incompatibilities .
Deprecated | Introduces the deprecation of an existing feature.

List of Updates (Change Log)

Following is an overview of all updates in this release which affect the public API. Please note that internal refactorings are not listed. For a full list of updates, please refer to the CVS repository and diff to the tag TrueZIP-6_4.

Cross Package Updates

Enhanced: Javadoc in all packages and many classes.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.crypto.io

Fixed: CipherReadOnlyFile.read() returned a negative integer for bytes in the inclusive range 128 to 255.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io

Fixed: File.deleteAll() bypassed the internal state associated with archive files.
Fixed: The copy operations in the File class threw an IOException instead of a FileNotFoundException if a file archive entry should get copied over a directory archive entry.
Fixed: The package internal ArchiveControllers class now forces the key manager singleton to get loaded and instanctiated at startup rather than on demand. With on-demand key manager instantiation, this may have been deferred until the JVM shutdown hook is run. However, some environments (app servers) inhibit class loading in shutdown hooks.
Fixed: ChainableIOException.initCause(Throwable) now throws a ClassCastException if parameter is not an IOException.
Changed: Newly created directory entries are now written to an archive file only if they have been created with File.mkdir() or their last modification time has been set with File.setLastModified(long). This mimics the behavior of most archive tools, which do not write directory entries.
Changed: The method DefaultArchiveDetector.getArchiveDriver(String) now throws a RuntimeException if an archive driver class cannot get loaded or instantiated. Previously, a WARNING message was logged using java.util.logging and null was returned.
Enhanced: When copying or renaming archive files, ghost directories in the source are now retained as ghost directories in the destination instead of being created as regular directories.
Enhanced: When an archive file is automatically unmounted, the archive controller now waits for all entry streams to get closed instead of failing with an exception if any open entry streams are present. This is supported by the auto-close feature of entry streams, which closes an entry stream if gets picked up by the garbage collector.
Enhanced: The file system now enumerates all entries in order via LinkedHashMap. This causes the order of entries to be preserved when copying archives, with the exception that all file entries are written before their directory entries.
Enhanced: Archive drivers are now already created when constructing a DefaultArchiveDetector rather than when getArchiveDetector(String) is called in order to make the class fail early. This does not affect loading the global registry from configuration files on the class path. Another positive side effect is that there doesn't need to exist a separate archive driver for any archive file suffix any more, which slightly reduces the memory footprint. However, archive drivers are still not singletons.
Enhanced: Removed redundant call to System.runFinalization() in ArchiveControllers.umount().
Enhanced: Setting the system property de.schlichtherle.io.strict to true now causes File.isLenient() to return false by default.
Enhanced: (In|Out)putArchiveMetaData don't trigger garbage collection and finalization any more if File.isLenient() returns false.
Enhanced: The system property de.schlichtherle.io.registry can now be set to a list of relative paths which are separated by path separators (';' on Windows, ':' on Unix). These relative paths are then searched for configuration files on the class path.
Enhanced: The system property de.schlichtherle.io.default can now be set to the list of archive file suffixes recognized by default. This overrules the DEFAULT keyword found in configuration files.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi

Fixed: AbstractArchiveDriver did not initialize the thread local encoder when deserialized.
Changed: Deprecated OutputArchive.storeDirectory(), since the same can be done with OutputArchive.getOutputStream() and a subsequent OutputStream.close() on the returned stream.
New: The new class MultiplexedOutputArchive provides concurrent writing of multiple archive entries by decorating arbitrary OutputArchive implementations. This eases the task of implementing an archive driver and benefits the client application because it allows concurrent writing of archive entries by multiple threads. Note that the TAR driver family already provided this feature before via a custom implementation. In this version, the implementation has been refactored to use the new class.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.tar

Fixed: TarInputStream did not recover all entry attributes properly. This resulted in unwanted changes of the attributes when a TAR file was updated.
Fixed: If a TAR file contained multiple entries for the same name, some temporary files may have been left.
Fixed: Entries created with new TarEntry(String) did not return -1 as their last modification time. This did not affect previous releases, but would have affected this release due to update #1 in the package de.schlichtherle.io.
Fixed: The TAR driver left a temporary file if a corrupted TAR file was read.
Fixed: The TAR driver now produces GNU tar compatible file headers for long file names instead of allowing the class TarOutputStream in the package org.apache.tools.tar from ant.jar to throw an (undocumented) RuntimeException.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip

New: The classes OdfDriver and OdfOutputArchive support reading and writing of OpenDocument Format (ODF) files. For more information, please refer to the Javadoc for the driver class.
Enhanced: The ZIP driver family now supports concurrent writing of multiple archive entries. See update #3 in the package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.rof

Fixed: BufferedReadOnlyFile.read() returned a negative integer for bytes in the inclusive range 128 to 255.
Fixed: ChannelReadOnlyFile.read() returned EOF after first use.
Fixed: ChannelReadOnlyFile.seek(long) threw IllegalArgumentException instead of IOException on negative offset.
Fixed: The class MemoryMappedReadOnlyFile did not work.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.swing

Fixed: Illegal call to FileSystemView.getSystemIcon(java.io.File) for nonexistant file argument.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.swing.tree

Fixed: FileTreeModel.nodeRemoved(java.io.File) did not properly notify the tree of updates.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.key

Fixed: AbstractKeyProvider.getCreateKey() and AbstractKeyProvider.getOpenKey() might have returned null instead of throwing an UnknownKeyException.
Changed: Moved PromptingKeyManager.getKeyProvider(String) implementation to its abstract definition in the KeyManager base class and deprecated it. The client application cannot get affected adversely.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.util

New: The class de.schlichtherle.util.CanonicalStringSet is a convenient and powerful means to operate with expressions such as "ear|jar|war|zip".

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.util.zip

Fixed: The byte array for extra data in this class is now copied on any call to the getter or setter.
Fixed: BasicZipFile.RawCheckedInputStream.read() did not provide a dummy byte to the inflater on EOF. This caused errors when assertions were enabled, but otherwise did not seem to have affected the CRC-32 checking.
Fixed: BasicZipOutputStream.write(int) wasn't overridden in ZipOutputStream.
Fixed: BasicZipFile.length() threw NullPointerException instead of an IOException if the file was close()d before.
Enhanced: The package now supports language encoding according to Appendix D of PKWARE's ZIP File Format Specification. This implies that the BasicZipFile class ignores its constructor parameter for the encoding if bit 11 of the General Purpose Bit Flag is set in an archive file.
Enhanced: BasicZipFile now enumerates its entries in the order of the Central Directory Records.
Enhanced: The property setters in the class ZipEntry now accept UNKNOWN (-1) as a value for numeric properties.
Enhanced: The constructor of BasicZipFile now fails if it finds an unsupported compression method in a Central Directory Record instead of waiting until getInputStream() is called.

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.7

(July 16th, 2010)

Contents

Introduction
List of Updates (Change Log)

Introduction

This is a feature and bug fix release. Upgrading is recommended for all users.

Transparent ZIP64 Support

This is the first release which supports ZIP64 extensions as introduced in version 4.5 of PKWARE's ZIP File Format Specification when reading or writing ZIP archive files with the low level API in the package de.schlichtherle.util.zip . This enables client applications to read and write ZIP archive files of more than 4GB size or with more than 65535 entries.

Handling ZIP64 extensions is fully transparent for client applications, so there are no public API changes involved. The only noticeable difference is that the setters and getters for the properties size and compressedSize (and the package private offset) in the class de.schlichtherle.util.zip.ZipEntry can now accept and return values ranging from 0L to Long.MAX_VALUE. Since these properties already had the primitive type long, this enhancement does not affect the binary compatibility of the JAR for TrueZIP 6.7.

In order to retain maximum interoperability with third party tools, by default, ZIP64 extensions are written to a ZIP file only if they are required. Currently, TrueZIP's implementation of ZIP64 extensions is known to interoperate round trip (create, update, read in both directions) with WinZip 11.1 and 7-Zip 4.56. Older versions of WinZip may work, but have not been tested. Older versions of 7-Zip (namely 4.42) are known to have problems reading ZIP files with ZIP64 extensions; please upgrade your copy of 7-Zip accordingly.

If the system property de.schlichtherle.util.zip.zip64ext is set to true (case is ignored), then ZIP64 extensions are always added when writing a ZIP archive file, regardless of its size. This feature is intended for testing purposes only. During normal operations, it should not be set as many third party tools would not treat the redundant ZIP64 extensions correctly. Note that it's impossible to inhibit ZIP64 extensions.

Enhanced ZIP File Interoperability

Some improvements were made on the interoperability of ZIP files created by TrueZIP with third party tools.

A minor bug has been fixed which caused some tools like e.g. the Windows Explorer not to be able to treat directory entries correctly.

ZIP files utilize a simplistic date/time conversion algorithm which isn't detailed in the ZIP File Format Specification version 6.3.2 from September 28th, 2007. Hence, for ZIP files the date/time conversion of the package java.util.zip is not fully interoperable with tools like Windows Explorer, WinZip 12.0 or 7-Zip 4.65. Symptoms are time stamps which may differ by two seconds or even an hour if the daylight saving time has changed between the last modification time of an archive entry and the current system time.

In order to address this issue, TrueZIP's equivalent to the package java.util.zip in the low level interface package de.schlichtherle.util.zip now offers a new class, DateTimeConverter. This class is now used by the class ZipEntry in order to perform the date/time conversion. By default, JAR file date/time conversion is selected in order to maintain backwards compatibility to the JSE implementation. If an application utilizing the low level interface needs ZIP file date/time conversion however, then it needs to subclass ZipEntry and override the method getDateTimeConverter().

For the high level API in the package de.schlichtherle.io the ArchiveDrivers for the ZIP and JAR file family have been updated to select the appropriate date/time conversion automatically. So users of the high level API don't need to do anything in order to benefit from the enhanced interoperability.

For additional information, please check the change log below.

Legend
New | Introduces a new feature.
Fixed | Introduces a bug fix of an existing feature.
Enhanced | Introduces the enhancement of an existing feature. This update is fully backwards compatible.
Changed | Introduces the change of an existing feature. This update may cause backwards incompatibilities .
Deprecated | Introduces the deprecation of an existing feature.

List of Updates (Change Log)

Following is an overview of all updates in this release which affect the public API. Please note that internal refactorings are not listed. For a full list of updates, please refer to the CVS repository and diff to the tag TrueZIP-6_6.

Cross Package Updates

Fixed & Enhanced: Updated the Javadoc of some classes.

Updates in the Default Package

Deprecated: The command line utility classes in this package are now deprecated in favour of the same classes in the package de.schlichtherle . This is a minor step intended for better interoperability with the OSGi Framework.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle

Changed: The visibility of the class CommandLineUtility has been changed to package private in order to reflect its very limited reusability. Client applications which sub classed this class should consider copying the source code instead.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io

Fixed: Files.isWritableOrCreatable(java.io.File) threw an IllegalArgumentException if and only if File.lastModified() returned a negative value. These files are now considered read-only (see issue #18).
Fixed: Files.isWritableOrCreatable(java.io.File) had a chance of leaving the first byte with its complement if the JVM gets killed unexpectedly (see issue #29).
Enhanced: File.cat() has been optimized a very little bit.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive

New: The interface Archive now provides the method getEnclArchive() in order to enable archive drivers to detect if they are working on an enclosed archive file.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.spi

Enhanced: The class AbstractArchiveDriver now logs details about the character set implementation at the CONFIG level.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip

New: With the advent of ZIP64 support in the package de.schlichtherle.util.zip the name prefix "Zip32" of some classes and methods in this package has become obsolete. Hence, new substitutes with "Zip" as their name prefix have been added. The obsoleted classes and methods with the "Zip32" name prefix are now marked as deprecated and have been retrofitted so that binary compatibility is retained.
Enhanced: The class ZipDriver (formerly Zip32Driver) and it's companion classes now utilize the newly introduced date/time conversion algorithm for ZIP files as implemented in the new object DateTimeConverter.ZIP in the low level API. Likewise, the class JarDriver and it's companion classes continue to utilize the existing date/time conversion algorithm for JAR files as implemented in the new object DateTimeConverter.JAR in the low level API. In the latter case, the effective behaviour of the API hasn't changed at all.
Enhanced: Where the constructors of the class ZipDriver and its subclasses accepted the compression level parameter to use when writing a ZIP archive, this parameter now accepts the value java.util.zip.Deflater.NO_COMPRESSION, too. Please note that the compression level is independent of the compression method and is only used for the default compression method de.schlichtherle.util.zip.DEFLATED.
Fixed: ZipEntry.clone() now throws an UnsupportedOperationException because cloning doesn't work with ArchiveEntryMetaData and is not required for ArchiveDrivers anyway.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.io.archive.zip.raes

New: With the advent of ZIP64 support in the package de.schlichtherle.util.zip the name prefix "Zip32" of some classes and methods in this package has become obsolete. Hence, new substitutes with "Zip" as their name prefix have been added. The obsoleted classes and methods with the "Zip32" name prefix are now marked as deprecated and have been retrofitted so that binary compatibility is retained.
New: The classes ParanoidZipRaesDriver and SafeZipRaesDriver now provide an additional constructor which accepts the default compression level as its sole parameter.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.util

Fixed: The class CanonicalStringSet had bad boolean return values for its methods addAll(CanonicalStringSet) and addAll(String) . This has been fixed to match the set analogy of the class.

Updates in the Package de.schlichtherle.util.zip

Enhanced: The classes BasicZipFile and BasicZipOutputStream now support ZIP64 extensions. For details and restrictions, please refer to their respective Javadoc.
Fixed: The class BasicZipOutputStream now writes MS-DOS compatible External File Attributes for directory entries in the Central Directory Header. This enhances the interoperability with some third party tools, e.g. the Exlorer in Microsoft Windows Vista.

New: The class DateTimeConverter can be used to determine the strategy for date/time conversion between the system time (Java time) and DOS date/time fields in ZIP archive files.

This class comes with two predefined instances: When using DateTimeConverter.JAR TrueZIP's date/time conversion strategy is compatible to:

Java SE: jar and java.util.zip package
Info-ZIP: unzip

When using DateTimeConverter.ZIP TrueZIP's date/time conversion strategy is compatible to:

Windows Vista Explorer (as of July 16th, 2010)
WinZip 12.0
7-Zip 4.65

Use with caution: Using these instances affects the interoperability of TrueZIP with third party tools!

New: The conversion of date/time values between Java and DOS in the class ZipEntry has been improved in interoperability: The new protected method getDateTimeConverter() is used to control the conversion of Java time to DOS date/time fields in ZIP archive files and vice versa. The implementation in this class returns DateTimeConverter.JAR for maximum compatibility with Java SE. Subclasses could override these methods to return other DateTimeConverter instances instead, e.g. DateTimeConverter.ZIP .
Enhanced: If assertions are enabled, a RuntimeException is now thrown if an illegal DOS date/time field is detected when reading ZIP archive files. This can be used to detect bogus ZIP archive files created by third party tools. The exception is actually thrown by the class DateTimeConverter , but usually exposed by the class ZipFile .